We may never [music] achieve a utopia,
but it is worthy and worth it to
attempt. But everything that's [music]
awesome in my life is kind of a cult. We
had to go over to the Windows team. They
wouldn't reply [music] to our emails.
They wouldn't fix our bugs. And we had
to go over there with a baseball bat. An
org like Microsoft can't. [music] Yes,
but a startup can. Yes, and every
startup must.
>> Gary,
so good to have you, brother. Thank you
so much for joining us today. Thanks for
having me.
>> Amazing, dude. Well, we're going to
cover a bunch of the basics, then we're
going to get into the advanced topics to
make sure that we kind of match the
curiosity and ambition of our audience.
>> That sounds great.
>> Does that work? Awesome. Well, dude,
maybe talk to me a bit about the
beginning of your journey 2003. You
know, it feels like what's under
discussed is founder psychology and then
sort of Silicon Valley culture and how
the two are connected. What did it feel
like when you first got in the game back
in 2003 coming out of Stanford?
>> I guess I wanted to work at startups,
but uh 2003 was funny in that like web
1.0 had just ended. Like the you know,
Nasdaq had just crashed and uh actually
there were no jobs that I could even
find in the Bay Area other than, you
know, working at Gap IT.
And so the two job offers I had were uh
Microsoft for Windows Mobile, which I
was pretty excited about, or Expedia.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, I you know, I had student loans
and I you know, while I wanted to start
a company, I just you know, felt like I
needed to get a job and then actually
there were no jobs in the Bay. So, it's
like kind of hard to believe actually
uh that moment was so bleak. And then
right before web 2.0,
>> it felt like it might have been the end
of tech, huh?
>> Right, a little bit. Yeah, that's what
that was the vibe. And then you know, at
the end of the day like
that's the boom, that's the bust. Like
these things sort of happen over and
over again.
>> So, at the time did it feel high status
to work in tech or on startups?
>> Not at all. I mean, you know, it sort of
lost to the sands of time, but
um
I was still excited about tech though.
Um
you know, I had done a lot of web
programming and then one of my regrets
actually was um I was sort of chasing
what was hot instead of what was clearly
the thing I knew. Mark Zuckerberg was
probably doing Facemash um around then
around 2003 and then Facebook didn't
even exist yet um
and I was getting out of web programming
at exactly the wrong time.
>> Because it felt like that was the smart
thing to do.
>> Yeah, it was smart and you know, I mean
this is true now. Um
you know, in in front of all these
people at Startup School, uh you know, I
sort of started this don't LARP
>> Right.
>> um meme.
>> I saw that.
>> Uh but I think like that's
that's embedded in this idea that like
you should just be earnest
>> Yeah.
>> and then you shouldn't follow what the
crowd is saying, right? Like at that
moment people said the web was dead, but
that was sort of the perfect time to
work on web and social and things like
that. Um and you know, I didn't do it. I
I ran off and said like
"Oh, well, the next hot thing will be
mobile." So I wanted to work at Windows
Mobile, which was true, but um why I
give up like the thing that could have
been the next thing.
>> What I love about what you're saying
though is often when we hear earnest, we
think naive, but actually what it sounds
like you're saying is there's like
earnestness is a sort of result of
maturity and courage.
>> Courage is actually I think
the right thing.
>> Yes.
>> Like if you know something that's sort
of if someone just like comes and
contradicts you or even if like
a blog post or like someone on Twitter
uh contradicts you,
>> Yeah.
>> you're like, well, I I don't I don't
agree with that because I believe my own
direct experience.
>> Yes.
>> I know that I'm not a time traveler
because if I was a time traveler, I
would have I would have sent a message
back to myself and said, "Just stay on
working on web stuff." Like you
literally have
um 5 years of experience on top of
everyone else. Like you could do an end
run around everyone. Like you could have
built like any kind of social software.
>> Yes.
>> But instead I was, um, you know, I was
22. So I was like being whipped around
by, uh, whatever I could read in The
Wall Street Journal. And, you know, I
the the classic question I'm sure you
get that, you know, all investors get
all the time is, "What's hot and what
should I work on?"
>> Right.
>> And that's the wrong question to ask.
Like the right question is like, "What
are you interested in? What do you know
uniquely?" And so I was that's like, you
know, one of a great many mistakes I
made in my career. I feel like I'm a
little bit, uh, doomed to be the first
principle storyteller of, uh, all the
mistakes that I made
>> Well, I think that it's it's very
inspiring for founders to hear your own
journey and your own mistakes. And then
not feel so bad about the ones that
we've all made along the way.
>> I mean, maybe talk about the culture of
Silicon Valley today. You know, on one
hand maybe it was despondent 20 years
ago. It's crazy to think that was just
23 years ago that you're talking about.
Um, now you think we would all be
incredibly elated, yet there's this
undercurrent. Maybe it's the LARPing
thing that you mentioned. You know, it's
being outside of the light cone, the
permanent underclass. Where does that
come from? Do you think there's any
truth in it? Talk through that.
>> I mean, I get it. Like there's just more
competition than ever. And then, um,
I think maybe it's just that we're
spending too much time in distribution.
I think Chris Dixon talks about this all
the time where, um,
you know, you're in the idea maze, but
you know, the cool parts of the idea
maze are like the weird fringe parts,
actually. It's always like, uh, what is
a toy? Like and that's the pattern in
Silicon Valley over and over again that
bears repeating, right?
>> Yes.
>> Like the idea that you could have a
computer on every desk in every home.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, today is like, of course, like
that's what's come to pass. But
>> the people who created that thing, they
were fringe weirdo punks, actually.
>> Yes.
>> Uh
>> They were outsiders. I mean, Homebrew
Computer Club was not where you were
getting laid.
>> Yeah. That's right.
>> [laughter]
>> You You just were like following this
weird obsession that, you know, actually
I want my own computer.
>> And I think Chris has said this, too. I
think a good measure of how interesting
the thing is is can you find the edge?
>> Mhm.
>> And for the most interesting things, you
typically can't. Even if you find the
edge of the conversation, you can't find
the intellectual edge. Which I think is
a very good sign. I mean, I had this
growing up in the '80s, maybe you had
this, too. There was sort of one way to
be cool in grade school, and probably in
high school, and maybe when you got to
college, you kind of found your people.
And now I think one of the miracles of
being internet native generation is that
people find their people much sooner.
You find your people on Reddit, you find
your people on, you know, X or Insta or
whatever your network is.
>> Oh, yeah.
I mean, that's the coolest thing today.
Like, there's probably a subreddit,
there's probably um
a part of X, like, you know, some part
of teapot that is uh you know, this part
of Twitter that um
is just your set of super weird, but
like really, really into that thing.
>> Yeah.
>> And you can find your tribe more or less
instantly.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, can you talk a bit about the
culture of Silicon Valley? It felt like
10 years ago it was sort of, you know,
it was lower status to work on something
like Palantir, either because people
were nervous about doing things that
were too much in the national interest,
or because it was was sort of dismissed
as a services business. Now, it's
clearly one of the most important
companies in the world with one of the
most compelling CEOs. You were early
there. What did it feel like? Why did
you do it?
>> Yeah. I mean, uh I have a worse story
than that. I have another mistake story.
>> Okay.
>> Where um
uh Joe Lonsdale and Stephen Cohen uh
were my fraternity brothers at Stanford,
Phi Psi.
>> Uh
and then I had a job, and they were like
interns at Peter Thiel's hedge fund.
>> Okay.
>> And uh Peter has this thing where you're
supposed to like, you know, when you
start a thing, you write down on a piece
of paper all the smartest people
who you need to go and hire and like get
to join you. And so
they said, "Oh, both of them were like,
oh, let's go get Gary. He's up in
Seattle." Like they flew me down to have
dinner with him.
>> And he said, you know, Peter said, "I'm
so sure this is the right thing for you.
Like here's a check for 70 grand." That
was how much I made at Microsoft at the
time.
>> Yeah.
>> And I said, "Thank you very much, Mr.
Thiel, but I might get promoted to level
60 this year."
>> Oh, no.
>> Which I did.
>> [laughter]
>> But I think it's That was like a $2
billion to $4 billion mistake at this
point.
>> Oh, no.
>> And I think about it all the time. Like
basically, I did the same thing again.
It was like the same thing that got me
to go work on Windows Mobile instead of
>> Yeah.
>> um just staying on the thing that I knew
and loved.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh it happened again. I was like, well,
I don't know, you know, I was working
backwards from the map instead of
looking down at the territory and saying
like, oh, well, these are the smartest
people I know. Like Joe and Stefan were
among the smartest people I'd ever met.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and you know, if not them, like who
was I going to, you know, be a
co-founder with? Like it just, you know,
the universe was saying like this is the
thing you need to do. But all I cared
about was what was cool, what was hot,
what would a really good investor say?
>> Um
>> And the thing is like they're like going
off of uh a map.
>> Yeah.
>> And like you can see, you can look down,
you can look around, you can like have
first principles knowledge of what's
going on.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and you know, what they were doing is
like they were going to governments and
three-letter agencies. And it was clear
that um the things that really good
computer scientists in Palo Alto could
do and create
>> Yes.
>> uh DC did not have access to that. And
you know, it's funny how much that
thing that they had identified like
Peter and Joe and Stefan and later Alex
Karp identified.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
that like runs through almost everything
that we do
in Silicon Valley. It's just like uh the
future is already here. It's not evenly
distributed. And then that's where like
first principles knowledge or like just
viewing the world as a scientist is
actually very useful.
>> Yes.
>> Um and what a scientist does is, you
know, sure there's published papers, but
you go and you examine all the truths.
And what you find is that once you go
down into the experiment or you go down
and talk to the first party people who
are experiencing a thing experiencing a
thing.
>> Yes.
>> Um
then you learn secret knowledge. Then
you have gnosis. And so, uh you know,
from Palantir I definitely learned that
everything that's awesome in my life is
kind of a cult.
>> Yeah.
>> That starts with some sort of truth or
belief that flies in the face of an
orthodoxy, which is very punk actually.
>> Yes. Yes. Totally dude, that's very Rick
Rubin would approve.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah, well, actually what I love about
you're saying is that there's a
beautiful truth in the fact that you've
talked through some of these maybe
tragic misses, but you know, the lessons
are courage, the lessons are
earnestness, right? The lessons are when
your instincts are pulling you to work
with a set of people. So so maybe talk a
little bit about, you know, we talk a
lot about how Silicon Valley and the
magic is it takes outsiders and turns
them into insiders. And I feel like YC
is the ultimate distillation of that.
You know, you go from being two founders
perhaps from a foreign country to two
people with YC on their LinkedIn and
everybody now knows what that means.
>> Totally.
>> So talk about how that happens. Is it a
process? Is it a mindset? And how has it
changed over the years?
>> Um I mean, I have to credit Paul Graham
and Jessica Livingston and the original
founders including Trevor Blackwell and
Robert Morris. I mean,
uh what Paul and Jessica figured out was
that there are lots and lots of really
smart people who do not get access um to
Silicon Valley. I mean, I think in the
past you had to like go to the right
schools, you had to know the right
people sort of and if you didn't you'd
come to Silicon Valley and you'd try to
get invited to the right parties. There
was like a social network that you had
to crack. Um and then
uh that YC we have a pejorative for that
whole scene which it's like we call them
scenester's actually. Uh which is I mean
it's sort of a nod to like what you used
to have to do. Um and some people still
believe that's like how you do it.
All they did was say, you know what?
Like here's a here's a website, here's
12 questions, later we added like a
1-minute video. And uh people on the
other end who are builders are going to
try to give you a fair shake. And so
today we have uh you know, 16 equal
partners including myself and all of us
like went through YC and had successful
outcomes and um
I think there's something valuable to
that. They just, you know, welcome to
welcome to Silicon Valley. We just um
celebrated uh 7,000 people coming to San
Francisco. The majority of them the very
first time they came it's, you know, our
startup school every single year.
>> So incredible.
>> We kind of call it like uh birthright
but for tech.
>> It looked like the Roman Colosseum,
dude.
>> Yeah.
>> It was amazing.
>> Yeah. So I you know, I think that that's
the coolest thing about Silicon Valley.
Like you sort of it sort of doesn't
matter where you're from or who you are.
It just actually matters what your ideas
are and can you execute. The only other
thing that I'd say like YC people get
that a lot of people don't get is um a
community of people who you can be super
real with. It's like if you go to a
TechCrunch event, you look to the left,
you look to the right and it's like are
Are really going to be able to tell them
anything real? Like you're going to hold
your cards pretty close and uh you know,
you're going to say how you're doing and
they're going to say killing it and then
they're going to ask back and like oh,
I'm also killing it. I mean, honestly
founders
really need that. Like it's very
solitary. It's um you know, on the day
that you lose your best customer, on the
day that your best engineer quits, like
who you going to call? And if you have
no one like
>> The day your co-founder loses hope and
you're not allowed to.
>> Right.
>> That's a tough day, you know?
>> Yeah.
>> Talk about the historical upside sort of
surprises of like founder types,
business types, and the downside
surprises. What have you learned through
YC?
>> I mean, what's we're sort of in the
middle of a big transformation now, I
think.
>> Okay.
>> Um for the longest time we really really
believed that you needed co-founders and
I think that everything else being
equal, having co-founders is net really
really good.
>> Totally.
>> Um I think some of this is like the
beginning of a cult.
>> Yeah.
>> Like you know, a cult where there's only
one person and that person can't
convince anyone else to join them is
like you know, worse than a cult. It's
just like a crazy person actually.
>> Right, right, right.
>> Um I think this is like an old Derek
Sivers TED Talk, right? Where it's like
uh yeah, one person dancing in a field
is a crazy person.
>> Yes.
>> But um
you know, it's really the second person
>> [laughter]
>> who like gets up
>> That's right.
>> and joins that person like then you just
what you find is you know, suddenly 10
people are all dancing. Then it's a
party. Yeah, that's literally the TED
Talk.
>> Love it.
>> And um
I think there's something to that, but
you know, I think what's happening right
now with vibe coding and agentic coding
>> Yeah.
>> um literally any given person could be
400 of that person like from
two years like even like nine months ago
um you can be a multiple of yourself.
>> It's amazing.
>> yeah, and so
>> think founders are more ambitious than
they've ever been?
>> They should be.
>> Yes.
>> Um if anything, like that's the number
one thing that people should do
is realize that like don't chase your
success or my success. Like that was,
you know, when we were coming up. Like
>> right.
>> the game done changed.
>> [laughter]
>> You know, like you actually you can't
just do a SaaS thing. Like I you know, I
was just doing an analysis on my pure
SaaS and I was like, oh shoot, like
you know,
a pure like per seat SaaS thing, like
not totally clear it will exist in
another 5 or 10 years. Like it's
perfectly fine as a wedge, but if you're
doing that now in 2026, like you better
hope that that's like a leap to some
sort of moat around data or network
effects or something else, right?
Um and that's like
you know, if you
if we would time travel to like even 2
years ago, it's like SaaS was God, you
know, like the 10 20X like next 12
months uh revenue multiple was like, you
know, iron law.
And like it's hard to believe it was
like, oh yeah, no, that's not true at
all now.
>> Well, all this is you know, it's a
related thing that I love is that code
is no longer precious.
>> Mhm.
>> My god.
>> That's like
>> the things that we had to go through to
get something shipped. And that's why
you had to have this like sense that
what you were making was important with
a capital I.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And that actually flies against the kind
of beautiful truth we were just talking
about because often earnestness isn't
obviously important with a capital I. So
you pursue things that seem important
when most of the most important things
actually start out seeming actually
unimportant.
>> I know you've been all over this with G
stack and G brain and you know, when you
started out to build those things, with
the intention to like contribute to the
community or just explore your
interests?
>> Oh, I was just messing around. Like, you
know, uh what was it? I think Boris
Cherny came on Light Cone podcast and I
just felt like the urge to you know, and
a bunch of our mutual friends, like all
of them uh basically just started coding
again and I was like, oh something's
happening. I better start.
And then initially it was just messing
around. It's like, "Oh, I mean, what
would it be like to do and like make an
office hours?"
>> Yeah.
>> Um and then the craziest thing there was
like we had just started um
like recording all of our office hours,
actually. And then I could I had like a
few months of data, and there were like
very clear things that um the YC
partners used as like rhetorical devices
or ways to like draw out like a step
function in your ambition.
>> Mhm.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um and then what's funny is I have this
markdown file that is basically like the
perfect script on how to advise founders
to like increase their ambition.
>> Yeah.
>> And then I actually had to go into
Claude, and I said, "Reduce this by 90%.
Reduce the strength and intensity of
this prompt by 90%." And then I
open-sourced that.
>> [laughter]
>> Cuz some of it is like you got to come
and you know do YC stuff.
>> course.
It's well we'll take your favorite five.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Yeah. We can't give away the crown
jewels like for free.
This just a taste. The first one's free,
you know?
>> Well dude, Kevin caught this. I think it
was a G stacker G brain where deep in
the open source you'd said, "Please
apply to YC."
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. But only if you're a
top 10% user of Claude code.
>> Incredible.
>> Like based on whether you're um
thinking about users, like thoughtful
about your product and your design. Like
it's not Not everyone gets that message,
actually.
>> Yes. Yes. Well dude, I love that you're
doing it, and I love that you're doing
it so publicly because I think this
comes back to the earnestness point,
which is the whole thing about building
intuition at this moment is just using
the technology. Oh yeah. You know, and I
think that there's this feeling like,
"Oh, how can I possibly catch up?" Or
there's so much seriousness around it.
It's like, "No. Just use every model and
build completely trivial things for no
other reason to have a chassis with
which to learn the new technology.
>> I think the most exciting thing is like
you can just have ideas.
And then in the past it's like, "Oh,
well I had to be the PM. Let me write
the spec. Like let me make sure I have,
you know, one or two engineers. Like oh,
how are we going to do QA? Like there's
just all this stuff that you used to
have to worry about. And then now it's
like no, slash QA. Like it's done. Like,
you know, yeah, we tested it. It's good.
Like we have unit tests. Like 90% test
coverage, you know?
>> Totally. You know, it's like arranging
your Zen rock garden. It's just fun to
do it and the like the output doesn't
matter that much, which is why everybody
talks about coding agents, but very few
people are showing their work. Oh, yeah.
Cuz a lot of it is sort of low stakes
work and I think that's beautiful and
okay.
>> Yeah.
>> No, I mean and then I think it's crazy
to what degree like suddenly agency and
taste
like off the charts important now.
And then the hard part is like
helping people realize like just by the
act of doing it and exercising it, like
that's how you get better. It's I don't
actually think that like those things
are in innate or inborn. Like some
people have more of it coming out of the
womb per se, but
>> Sure.
>> you know, it's you just practice. You
know?
>> Well, let me challenge you on this cuz
Nikita said this a couple of maybe a
year ago and I thought it was
interesting, which is hey, we were told
that the like highest form of art and
business was, you know, film and
software. And now anyone can make films
and anybody can make software, yet the
same 20% who were originally doing it
are still the ones who are doing it.
Is there kind of this like is agency
something that you can, you know,
embrace or are there just people that
are naturally high agency and many that
are not?
>> Mhm. I mean, if I look at my own career,
like I would easily say that I'm a late
bloomer. And, you know, I had to make
these like ridiculous mistakes, like
saying no to Palantir or like leaving
web programming to like learn. And so,
I feel like my life is somewhat like a
testament to no, no, like I can make
mistakes and then I can introspect. I
can reason about them and then make
different choices.
>> Amazing.
>> That's the hope anyway.
>> Yeah, that is hope.
>> Talk a little bit about loops. I think
they're a kind of coding loops, um,
which are well discussed. And now the
graphs thing, which is sort of, you
know, both funny and and also real. But
it feels like the most interesting loops
are business loops.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Like how can you actually have a loop
where the output is changing the way the
business itself operates? I know that
Tom gave this great talk about how to
organize your company in that way.
>> Talk about how YC is organizing around
loops and how you're advising your
companies to.
>> Yeah, absolutely. I mean, I messed
around with Open Claw. I created G
Brain, which is kind of like Soda
Retrieval. Um,
I basically distill I earlier this year
I created Garyslist.org, which is sort
of like actually an agentic newsroom.
And then I had to create like really,
really good rag around like, you know,
uh, personal deep research just to be
able to put together some of those
articles.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh, and then all I did was like I had
Open Claw look at that repo, extract out
like the agentic rag part, especially
around like, um,
like after-the-fact uh, graph
generation.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, and then it just ended up being Soda
even against like Memory Palace and a
bunch of other open source.
>> Edible.
>> Uh, and then what I realized is that
just allows the agent to know what
million tokens to keep in its head for
any given task.
>> Yes.
>> And so, um, what's interesting is like I
think there are a couple things at work
right now, like, um,
the frontier model labs that are, you
you know, letting you use ChatGPT or
Claw, I think that they're still pretty
constrained on
and pretty constrained on, um, amount of
compute they want to give you. And so,
if you really want to token max, you
actually have to use something like
Hermes Agent or Open Claw.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, and then you have to like tune it
all the way up. Like you're just like,
give me like let me load a million
tokens or 800,000 tokens in
>> Yeah.
>> to any given request and like have that
be in your like soul.md.
>> Yeah. But when you do that, like I think
that you basically get to live in
2028. Like, you know, it costs, I don't
know, 50 or 100,000 dollars a year to
like use the agents at full strength,
like full 150 IQ on every request.
But you'll feel it more or less
immediately.
It just costs like a crazy amount. But
for a CEO or for a founder, it actually
makes a lot of sense to do that and you
have to give yourself permission to
token max in that way.
Um,
but you know, and then what you get is
like I get you get to live in 2028
today.
>> Amazing.
>> Um, but I think like going back to what
founders can do,
um,
if you live that way,
not only do you want to do that task,
you want to like skillify it. Like you
you do some like
feat of strength and then you turn it
into a markdown file plus code plus
tests that can be reused and like put
into a cron job.
>> Yes.
>> And so, uh, I think we're just seeing
like across the board, um,
a markdown file is an employee.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's an employee that, uh, will do
the job perfectly every single time and
it will do it like as many times as you
want.
>> Yeah.
>> And then, you know, at that point all
you're doing is like take any business
process that you need in your company
and you just do it once perfectly. And
the first time you try to do it, it's
going to be bad.
>> Expensive. Yeah, yes, many iterations.
>> Yeah. But then at the end you can you as
long as you can
tell very, very quickly and in in very
simple ways, like, "Hey agent, fix this,
fix that. Like this was wrong."
Um,
you know, the actual trace and the
actual, uh, history out of, um, that
agent, uh, working with you,
>> Mhm.
>> it'll actually turn that into a skill
file that's perfect, actually. And
anytime it screws up in like a future
case, it's just a bug fix, and then it's
there forever.
>> And this loop you would apply to sales,
to marketing, to customer support, to
everything.
>> Yeah, to everything.
>> Really interesting.
>> I mean, G stack was basically that for
engineering, right? It's like there's a
QA loop. I had to build something that
works with browsers to go and cuz that's
what I found like early with G stack, I
found myself um,
you know, automating how I thought about
PM, and then uh, you know, I had a
engineering skill that was like an
engine manager that made sure that there
was a unit test and end-to-end test
coverage.
>> Yep.
>> Um, but then in the end, I found myself
like
uh, I automated all the other things so
much that all I was doing at the end was
black box testing to to verify.
And it was like, "Oh, no, no, okay, like
even that part." Like it's interesting
like uh, building these agentic systems
today, I think that's all you're doing
is you're seeing where the bottlenecks
are, and then, you know, almost every
single time it's like,
"How do I just instruct the agent to
create a piece of software or a markdown
file that blows away that roadblock."
And then, when you take a step back and
you've done that for the whole task,
it's like, I mean, we we there are
companies now today that, you know, we
were we were talking about earlier
that's like literally you can go from
zero to 15 mil ARR in about 4 months
with like two or three people and like
hundreds of agent like, you know, a few
hundred skill files.
>> It's amazing. So, there's this like
recursive self-improvement and there's
this hill climbing that happens.
Like
at what point does it start to fall
over? Is there like do you need error
correction? Do the errors compound? Does
it get constrained by exception
handling, human relationships? Cuz
otherwise, these companies should just
be able to grow and run forever.
>> Yeah. I mean, I guess my experience
once you get a lot of markdown files or
yeah, anytime you have like some large
amount of data, um,
that's where like provenance matters.
That's where um conflict management sort
of you know when you have two facts if
you have provenance then you're like
well this is the more recent one like
this is the one that wins. You need a
cron job that's sort of sweeping through
that and making sure that things are
accurate and from the right places. Um
but these are things that I think as you
use the systems
um
you just know that you need to build
these things. Like anyone who's I mean
this is actually one of the interesting
things I think is an advantage for
founders in their 30s and 40s now.
>> Yeah.
>> Um like
I mean I think that there going to be as
many Patrick Collisons as ever.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but one mega trend that we're seeing
is like a 35 40 45 year old founder who
like been around the block.
>> Yeah yeah yeah.
>> Built a lot of companies.
I mean I think uh yeah Peter Steinberger
is like a perfect example of that. Where
it's like he's been around the block
like he knows what to build.
>> Yes.
>> Um and then if you take that person like
suddenly there's 400 of those people
like you can outperform an entire
department of like any mag seven.
>> I also think that if you've had some
experience in the enterprise there are
these dynamics that you know you can
seek to kind of mirror and explore. So
one of the things I'm really interested
in is conflict. Right? Most people at an
enterprise would say conflict is a bad
thing but I actually think that there's
this sort of productive constructive
conflict that at its best is the search
for truth.
>> Yeah.
>> These systems allow us to do things like
explore conflicting approaches and
totally unbundle it from the human
emotion. And I think that's actually
very important because this is why the
sort of the decentralization in an
organization or an economy works well
because every idea gets tried. You know?
>> Yeah uh do you know Pedro from Brex is
like the most aggressive person I've met
who does this with his exact team?
>> No.
>> So which is cool like he uses Like, he
actually was one of the people who like
really got me into OpenClaw.
>> Okay.
>> Um because he just came in and, you
know, he had lunch with us at YC.
>> Yeah.
>> And he just walked us through um you
know, the the vibe around OpenClaw was
that it was too unsafe and dangerous and
like delete your whole computer and
stuff like that. Uh what he ended up
doing was like building an entire
open-source layer, which he actually has
open-source called Craptrack.
>> Okay.
>> But it's like an agent that watches all
the network traffic and all the things
that uh OpenClaw does.
>> Nice.
>> And then that's how he squares the
circle. Like, Brex is one of the most
regulated, you know, fintech. Of course.
Of course. Um And then the upshot of
what he got is that um he has his agent
look at the meeting transcripts from
like all of his direct reports. And he
like can see that like two levels down.
Yeah. And then the thing that really
jumped out at me is like he can use
uh meetings that he's not in now to
figure out like what's broken, what's in
conflict, like who's who's in conflict
with who.
>> Yes.
>> Uh and then sometimes he can show up at
a meeting. He has perfect context from
like the last 3 weeks of like that one
compliance team.
>> Yes.
>> And then he can walk in and he's like,
"Actually, you're right. We're doing it
your way." And then he can leave.
>> That's so badass.
>> Yeah. And it's like, can you imagine
like that is actually one of the
defining reasons why um startups or
businesses fail.
>> Yes.
>> It's like it's actually like a a
management challenge. Like, the business
becomes too big to fit in one person's
head. And then this is like the most
profound form of you have you have
agents, you have memory, you have
retrieval. Um you like zap the rocks
more, the rocks give you like raw
intelligence about like what's
happening. And it can actually
introspect not just on the opinion of
like someone two levels down in your
organization, but it can actually look
at the ground truth from the data,
right? And it's like that, you know,
that's clairvoyance, right? Like
>> Yes.
>> You I mean
if you once you have that in your brain,
like actually every business in the
world is available for you to take their
business.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> like the world is basically built on
things that are built around human
beings and human beings can only keep
seven plus or minus two things in their
head at any given time.
>> And you know, guess what? You plus an
agent can keep basically three Harry
Potter books in your head. You can like
rifle shot
>> come.
>> Yeah, I mean and more to come, right?
Like this is as this is as bad there's
so many cryptoisms that like applied
like 10 times more to AI which is like
this is the worst it will ever be
actually.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Um and so the whole world, like all
business, all things that people rely
on, government especially, uh is
basically still built on a world that is
predicated by human beings, limited
human beings that can only keep seven
plus or minus two things in their head.
>> Yes.
>> And it's not ready. Like it's not ready
for the world where agents can think at
the speed of light. Like you have
unlimited amounts of it, like unlimited
amounts of data. Um and then, you know,
my hope is that like basically products
are going to be 10 or 100 times better.
Like they should be a thousand times
better.
>> Yes.
>> Like services should be a thousand times
better, right? Like
>> Yes.
>> you know, the invisible hand of
capitalism at that point lies properly
done, it's not about lowering the cost
of something. It should actually be um
creating these like sort of magical
things that they I was like on Wall
Street Journal podcast recently and the
reporter like kept trying to like gotcha
me. He kept saying like, are you you
know, you guys in tech, are you trying
to make a utopia? And I was like this is
a trap. Like I don't I I would not go so
far to say,
you know, but as I went through like a
bunch of examples from like a bunch of
the startups that you and I have like
worked on and funded and things like
that. I was like, actually like maybe,
right? Like
you know, we may never achieve a utopia,
but it is worthy and worth it to
attempt, right? And that, you know, I I
would not say that Silicon Valley or
tech will achieve a utopia. I will very
earnestly say that we are trying to
bring about a better world.
>> Maybe another way to say this is just
this is the least happy you'll ever be.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, because I think it like one of
the other implications of what you're
describing is just the ergonomics of the
sort of white-collar job today. You
know, you think about every You've
worked at big companies. Like you think
of just the kind of morass that you have
to get through.
>> Torture.
>> You think of how lossy the communication
is. Like the entire management science
sort of managerial class. Like maybe
that was a 100-year distraction from
what was founder mode, you know, in the
in the Industrial Revolution all the way
through Henry Ford, all the way through
some of the early Silicon Valley
founders, and then everybody just kind
of hit this tidal wave of management.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Now we have this new model that can lead
to dramatic productivity improvements
like 3 days a week of really intentional
work. Maybe 1 day.
>> Yeah.
>> And the other days you're touching
grass. And I think the time that you do
spend is just so much less burdened by
this stuff
>> that you always felt like you had to
wade through.
>> Yeah, that's right. I mean, if you look
at the typical Mag 7 day-to-day, it's
insane. Like I remember when I was 22
working on Windows Mobile.
Uh we're working on
you know, these crazy devices that were
like years before the iPhone. And um
we needed integration for instance from
the Windows team, which was like, you
know, on the other side of the highway
in Redmond.
>> Right.
>> And then I remember, you know, me and my
sort of PM mentor,
uh we had to go over to the to the
Windows team and like they wouldn't
reply to our emails. They wouldn't fix
our bugs. They wouldn't even like mark
it as won't fix. They just ignored us.
And we had to go over there with a
baseball bat. Like I don't know why he
brought one. Like it wasn't like he was
going to like rough anyone up. It was
just like this vague threat or
something.
It was actually hilarious and I think
about that all the time. It's like what
kind of like bureau cratic hell is it
where like two perfectly smart people
who are making like good tech money,
>> Yeah.
>> you know, are put into a situation where
like there's a fiefdom over here. Like
literally there's like seven levels
between us and that person.
>> Yes.
>> And this person doesn't even know that
we spent like four hours trying to get
like a P3 bug fix that was like a
blocker for a thousand of our users or
something. It's like
>> And how much humanity is just wasted?
>> Yeah.
>> How many 2:00 a.m. sort of anxious
wake-ups were there
>> Yeah.
>> because somebody wanted to not have a
hard conversation. Like it's, you know,
it's it's a really it's a waste of the
way we should be spending our time in
working.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's a profound version of like
the seven plus or minus two. Like I
don't think that like the, you know,
product unit manager or whatever the
heck their, you know, their title was.
Like I don't think that they wanted us
to waste our time like that.
I think it's just that, you know, your
day like you just don't have enough
hours in the day and we're like
incredibly limited human beings, but you
know,
I yeah, it's funny. Like I think that
you know, I think about my time at
Microsoft and it's like I remember
getting an iPod and like doing
competitive research for like Windows
Mobile versus the iPod. I can imagine
today at Microsoft you can imagine a
markdown file and a skill
>> Yeah.
>> that is run on a cron.
>> Yes.
>> And it's like how are how are all the
people working on this team? Like, are
they blocked? Who are they blocked by?
What are the external dependencies? Like
suddenly there is a graph, there's a
loop, and then suddenly like, you know,
the products can actually just move that
like, you could release something in a
day or two that would have taken like 6
months. It's incredible. And if you
could like multiply that out across
like, the thing is like probably an org
like Microsoft can't.
>> Yes.
>> But like a startup can.
>> And every startup must.
>> Yes, they must be organized as well. I
also love what you said, it's almost
like the mid-level of bureaucracy should
be agents. Cuz I actually think that,
you know, being in charge is somewhat
overstated. Like I love to actually have
at least the mid-level organize the
work, you know, resolve the conflicts
that it can somewhat programmatically,
probabilistically programmatically. Of
course, the executive team maybe sets
direction, the individual sort of
decides on execution, but just the whole
organization layer, which a lot of
product managers historically did,
should not be human.
>> I mean, the great thing is um it doesn't
have to be Do you know how uh Venkatesh
Rao has this thing where it's like, you
need to be above the API line? Like if
Uber came out, like if you're an Uber
driver, you're below the API line. Like
you should be fighting to be above the
API line. I actually think AI erases the
API line. Um like one of the funniest
things I saw recently is uh there's a
API company um that we funded called
Kolabtree,
and they released a um
a bug report endpoint that is not for
humans to use, it's for agents who use
their software to use. And there's an
LLM where it's like if there's a bug in
the software,
um
it like the bug report goes, but then it
replies real time.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's like, actually like, that's a
good bug, we filed it, we're going to
fix it next week, but also like try this
workaround.
>> Wow.
>> And then like, I can't get that out of
my head because you could imagine um
that could be how companies work, right?
Um
like instead of being below the API line
and having to do what like, I don't
know, the API tells you to do.
>> Mhm.
>> Like this can be a back and forth
>> actually. And then I always think about
um you the reason why cars in the '80s
got so good in Japan
>> Mhm.
>> was uh it was actually a management
technique. Like they realized the Toyota
production system
>> That's right.
>> meant that like if you are the person
doing the work on the line, you should
be allowed to change the line because
you are the person with the most amount
of contacts
>> Yes.
>> to be able to improve your own working
situation. And that's why American cars
really started sucking and why Japanese
cars became absolutely incredible. It's
like this very subtle simple way that
actually empowers the worker. And so
there's a sort of like mix that I think
is interesting.
>> interesting cuz what's traditionally
seen as a hierarchical society came up
with this very bottom-up way of working
which led to like arguably a 40-year
generational run because of process
power.
>> Yeah.
Which is beautiful.
>> How How many As you think about kind of
our evolution towards this vision, how
many of these problems do you think are
intelligence-bound?
Like we need smarter models versus there
will be other attributes of models that
will unlock success.
>> I mean, honestly, it's all human
>> Uh
>> humans are the ones who are going to
like slow this down.
>> And then
>> Um
>> actually I'm realizing this might be a
white pill.
>> Okay.
>> So if you look at like the tenor of
what's going on just broadly in the
discourse about AI, it's all like this
sort of doom and gloom like all
white-collar jobs are going to go away.
There's going to be a permanent
underclass.
>> Yes.
>> And then
uh
funny enough what I think is
>> Um
>> all of the bureaucracy and the slowness
and the seven plus or minus two
>> Uh
>> of like every company, every
institution, every organization, all the
middle managers in the world.
>> Yeah.
>> That is actually the white pill.
>> 100%.
>> So
you know
these things are going to be slower than
you think.
>> Yes.
>> Right? Uh I looked at you know, we had
7,000 people. Most of them were 18 to 22
years old.
>> Amazing.
>> And I looked in their faces and like
they're all AI native. Like they were
born more or less like, you know, they
became adults in the time of ChatGPT.
>> Yes.
>> Uh and it's going to you know, and for
us it's like now we, you know, run
which is nice.
>> That's great, right?
>> But, you know, imagine us like 20 years
ago. Like, you know, we were the ones
who were native to the web. We were the
ones who were native to mobile. Um and
then now we run so then all of
society runs on the things that we
expected from when we were 18 to 22. So,
I think that, you know, the white pill
to me is like it's going to be 20 years
and that's not a bad thing. That's
actually a good thing.
>> Yes.
>> Um like society is way slower than you
think. Government is way slower than you
think. Every company in the world is way
slower than you think.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and there are real motes to these
things. Like there are structural
reasons why a Microsoft isn't going
anywhere.
>> Yes.
>> Um and then I guess this is sort of a
little antithetical to what most, you
know, most people in Silicon Valley
would say like, "I want to start up to
replace all of them."
>> Yeah.
>> Uh and the reality is like they won't,
you know?
>> They won't. I love it. Okay, I have two
more questions for you. Um you know, one
on this kind of sort of trying to
envision the near future, what do you
think the next computer looks like? What
does a new computer look like?
>> Oh, man.
I think in the short term it'll probably
keep looking like the way it is, but it
seems inconceivable that um it'll stay
that form factor. Like it's pretty
clearly going to be voice.
>> Yes.
>> I think there's a lot around memory. Um
it's going to take a while to you know,
to we're we're at this moment where
everyone's sort of happy with ChatGPT or
Claude Co-work or whatever it is.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
but I don't think they will be in the
long term. Like, um
I think you're going to want a lot more
context, and you're going to want like
all watched over by machines of living
grace. Like, you're going to want this
thing that uh is benevolent, knows about
like your hopes, fears, and desires, and
then is sort of like relentlessly
searching to help you in that way. And
that's actually going to be really
exciting. And you know, the path through
that will probably be like computer use,
memory, like uh diarization, like
ingestion, like um
Yeah, I mean
I think there's going to be a lot there.
And uh you know, the cool thing is
it's actually going to take longer.
Like, this isn't a Like, I don't think
people are even talking about this now.
My guess is like next year, 2027, will
be like the harness wars.
>> Yes.
>> You know, and then uh but it's really a
cost thing. Like, it's just too
expensive right now,
>> Yes.
>> you know? Um
but it won't be it Like, there will be a
war for a billion consumers
>> Yes.
>> uh right when like the frontier pure
model compute of today
>> Yeah.
>> will be like maybe 50 or 100 bucks in
like two or three years.
>> Yeah.
>> And then that will be when like the most
few the browser wars will be back on.
>> Yes. Yes. Well, we're already seeing it
like the price per token of frontier is
going to infinity. Like, my thesis is
infinity dollars a token, you can't have
it. And the price per token of the model
that was frontier a week ago is
collapsing to zero. And I actually think
to me that is a huge white pill for a
lot of reasons. You know, one of the
most important of which is just we need
more consumer AI software. And in a
world where most consumer products are
free to try, you just can't do that when
you have really high costs of
incremental distribution. The magic of
software is zero cost incremental
distribution.
We have these magical primitives. Like,
we have computers that are emotive and
have emotional texture for the first
time in 40 or 50 years. What a tragedy
that we haven't built more ambitious
consumer products yet.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I'm really excited for this sort of
changing economics of models to unlock
these new categories.
>> I mean and we're so early. Like I was
convinced that
like being becoming a convert to open
claw made me very very convinced that it
was going to happen right away and then
at this point I'm like that's not
correct at all. Like
>> Yeah. Well, you should try the new chat
GPT desktop app actually has got a voice
mode and it's sort of it's an operator
or a concierge that can see all your
threads.
>> Oh, cool.
>> And you can access it from your phone.
It's very open claw-ish and I'm sure
Peter had his hands all over it. To me
it's the closest thing we've seen yet to
a true consumer assistant.
>> Oh, I can see it's awesome.
>> Yeah, yeah. Chat GPT always had like
basically the best memory. So I got to
try it again.
>> They've done a great job.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, last question
you know, we talked a lot about kind of
utopian visions for the world and
problems that are maybe intelligence
bound. You've also put a lot of energy
into sort of local politics and doing
things I think are very pro-social, but
it seems like more of those problems are
human coordination bound.
>> Oh, definitely.
>> Yeah, how do you get energy to do that
work? You know, is there a white pill
for that aspect of our society? Maybe
talk a bit about that.
>> I mean the white pill is just believing
that America still has rule of law and
that
people in government are trying to help
and like somewhat earnest. Like it's not
perfect.
I think that the white pill for me
recently was even just doing jury duty
in San Francisco and to see like this
orderly process of really a
cross-section of San Francisco.
One thing I realized was like actually
we are a big part of the city. Like
we're
10 20% of the people are like directly
working in tech.
>> Yeah.
>> And so um
to see something that was
I mean the judge was really good. I mean
it was a horrible case, but like
you know, government
is not here to like ruin people. Like
>> Yeah.
>> And so and then at that point um we can
vote.
>> Yes.
>> Like we actually have a say
and then I think everything is
downstream of media at that point. Like
I think the San Francisco moment that
got me very engaged was realizing
you know Asian Americans are 25% of the
voting populace about 30% of the
population but during COVID like we had
a district attorney who was turning a
blind eye to some of the most heinous
crimes against our elders
and simultaneous to that we had a school
board that was openly hostile against
Asian American kids who just wanted to
learn algebra in public middle school
which hit me because
I was that public school kid in Fremont
in the East Bay. Like if I couldn't have
taken algebra in middle school, I
couldn't take calculus by senior year. I
wouldn't have been able to study
engineering at Stanford and I wouldn't
be here doing any of the things I get to
do today and I'm like oh okay now now
they've made it personal and like let me
understand and it turned out to be like
sort of all the same people the same
people who want to destroy all the data
same people who
don't want to build any housing in
anywhere in California or the world.
Like it's sort of Nimbys who want to
virtue signal who
sort of have these ideologies that like
don't square with mine. I mean as a
builder you like well you know words
have meaning like supply and demand
exists markets exist like incentives
exist and then
you know I think that government is what
you know when people like us don't speak
up
when we don't like pay attention and
like hold our media accountable not just
the government
then things get very deranged and that's
what San Francisco was I think around
COVID and then just by
sheer organization like this is I think
that like the Chinese of the West Side
organizing around algebra and
you know
the deaths of our elders
going to farmers markets and like
literally physically like telling each
other they're killing us and they're
killing us right um
ABC News
you know literally the meat the
mainstream media
TV channel of San Francisco and the Bay
Area would not cover
anti-Chinese and anti-Asian crime.
And
you know
I I it's like unconscionable right like
our institutions failed us and the great
thing is like
when the system becomes so odious you've
got to put your body on it. I think that
was Mario Savio.
And it's kind of I mean it's ironic
almost to like say that but on the other
hand like that's what I believe like
they can't do this to us and we're going
to stop it. And even at like personal
peril even at
you know reputational cost like we
should be willing to take that cost
because that's our covenant with our
fellow man and our fellow citizen you
know and if we don't do it who's going
to do it like nobody does it and I'm
super proud of what we're doing in San
Francisco because we have beat back that
ideological
set of people who like created this mess
and you know it's not perfect in San
Francisco but it's getting better.
>> It's amazing right now.
>> I mean I think I saw that Lori might be
the most popular mayor or politician in
the entire country. Yeah. Things have
gotten so much better. Everybody sees it
feels it in the vibe. Some people say I
wonder why but I think for those of us
who know we see that your sort of
stewardship not just of the industry of
the startup community of sort of
technology but also of the community is
one of the big catalysts. So thank you
for doing that work.
>> Thank you so much. Yeah. So and I think
San Francisco should be the beacon for
pushing this back in every blue city in
America as you know I that's what Gary's
list.org is basically like how do we
take the lessons that we learned here
and like LA needs this, New York needs
this, Minneapolis needs this, Seattle
needs this.
>> Well, and also let's find you know to
connect the two that sort of you know
culture society and technology like
let's find very local ways for the
ambition that this technology unlocks to
show up. You know, I was in London last
week and you were talking a little bit
what's possible. It's like hey, you
don't have to have an American vision
for how AI impacts your society. If you
want the NHS to be incredible
then like you can do that with this
technology. So the kind of the
opportunity for ambition to be very
localized in our communities. I think is
something really interesting.
>> Yeah, and so yeah, act local like
take care of the people right next to
you like you know, I I think it's funny
uh
so many people get very very obsessed
with national. I mean we want to look at
national generally right now. It's like
you know what? Like I care about San
Francisco, I care about housing, I care
about crime, I care about uh you know,
treatment and recovery
>> Yeah.
>> and if we do that like we can have the
society we want to live in and then you
know, if we fix local like state and
national will fix itself cuz like on a
five or 10 year basis like the people
who win up there like [music] they they
will come up through a system that's
functional and about saying no to things
that don't make sense, about saying yes
to the things that are awesome for the
people.
>> I love it. All right, Gary. First of
many. Thanks, brother. [music]
>> Thanks, bro.
>> This is great.
>> Cool. Yeah.